Guide to the Henry David Gray Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Henry David Gray Papers
1924-1981
RG 52
Yale University Divinity School Library
66
(104 boxes)
These papers provide extensive biographical information about Gray as well as unique and valuable documentation of the merger between Congregational Christian Churches and the Evangelical and Reformed Church to form the United Church of Christ in 1957. Henry David Gray (1913- ) was a Congregational minister who served churches in South Hadley, Massachusetts, (1935 -1939), South Pasadena, California (1942-1955), Hartford, Connecticut (1955-1970), and others. He was active in youth work, leading eight "odysseys" overseas and coordinating youth assemblies. He was one of the founders of the National Association of Congregational Christian Churches, the group of continuing Congregationalists formed following the merger of the Congregational Christian Churches and the Evangelical and Reformed Church to form the United Church of Christ in 1957.
Gray, Henry David, 1908-
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Henry David Gray
Biographical / Historical
1908 Jan 18 Henry David Gray born in Antrim, Northern Ireland, son of Nathaniel and Margaret Lawther Gray.
1919 Emigrated first to Canada, then in 1923 to the Los Angeles area
1928-1929 Director of Youth, Bethel Congregational Church, Ontario, California
1929-1930 Assistant minister, First Methodist Church, Pomona, California
1930 B.A., Pomona College, magna cum laude, Phi Beta Kappa
1930-1931 Director of youth work, Center Congregational Church, Hartford, CT
1931 Boston University School of Theology, religious education courses (summer)
1931-1933 Religious education director, Asylum Hill Congregational Church, Hartford
1933 B.D., Hartford Theological Seminary, awarded William Thompson Fellowship
1933-1935 Minister, Hope Park and Buccleuch Congregational Church, Edinburgh, Scotland
1935 Ph.D., University of Edinburgh
1935 Study at Tubingen University, Germany
1935-1939 Minister, First Congregational Church, South Hadley, Massachusetts
1939-1942 National Secretary for High School and Student Work of the Congregational Christian fellowship
1942-1955 Minister, Oneonta Congregational Church, South Pasadena, California
1945 Member of team to investigate war damage in British Congregational Churches
1948 First of eight "Youth Odysseys" led by HDG
1949 Convened First International Congregational Youth Assembly
1954 Honorary Doctorate of Divinity, Pomona College
1955-1970 Minister, South Congregational Church, Hartford, Connecticut
1955 One of the founders of the National Association of Congregational Christian Churches
1962-1966 Editor, The Congregationalist
1971 Interim minister, Hollywood Congregational Church
1971-1972 Interim minister, Congregational Church of the Valley
1972- Established, served as dean of Hollywood Congregational Center for Study and Service/ now known as American Congregational Center; Editor, Congregational Journal
1985, 1989 Coordinated C-Way: Congregational World Youth Assembly (re-establishment of 1949 Congregational Youth Assembly)
Partial list of organizations served:
General Council of Congregational Christian Churches
National Association of Congregational Christian Churches
Board of Home Missions, Congregational Christian Churches
American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions
Connecticut Congregational Fellowship
Hartford City Planning Commission
McCall Mission
Corporation for Lady Doak College of Madurai, India
Rural Resources Development Project in Jordan
Ventura County Historical Association
Santa Monica Mountains Commission
Moderator:
Hampshire Association, MA
Los Angeles Association, CA
Connecticut Fellowship
National Association (CCC/NA)
Founding member:
National Council of Churches (Nov. 1950)
Pasadena Council of Churches
Board of Directors:
Greater Hartford Council of Churches
South Pasadena Council of Churches
Church Federation of Los Angeles
Scope and Contents
I. Personal files/ correspondence
II. Churches served
III. The Christian year
IV. Youth files
V. Odyssey files
VI. Writings, addresses, sermons
VII. Congregational records
In an autobiographical sketch written by Henry David Gray, he listed the major accomplishments of his life as follows:
1. Community service through leadership of youth and urban/regional/state planning
2. Founded two national church youth groups.... Convened 1st international Congregational youth assembly, 1949
3. Fifty+ men and women into full-time Christian service
4. Half million miles, 36 countries/cultures, leading 200+ teenagers, 9 Odysseys
5. Award-winning new-modern-classic church architecture in California and Connecticut
6. Only thorough report on Congregational polity, documents, usage ever made
7. Preparation/production over 100 multi-medium services: art, drama, music, literature, choral-reading, choreography...
8. Transformation of downtown City of Hartford through City Planning role.
9. New economic-agricultural-village life-base in Jordan through Rural Resources Development Program
10."Congregational Worshipbook" unique resource compendium for individual and/or group worship and rites, 1990 rev. ed., 788 pp.
All of these accomplishments are well documented by the Henry David Gray Papers except his work in the area of urban/regional/state planning and the activities of the Rural Resources Development Program. Gray's files relating to urban/regional/state planning have been deposited at the University of Connecticut, Portland State University, and the California Historical Society, though sufficient samples remain in this manuscript group to indicate the scope of his work.
The papers of Henry David Gray in Manuscript Group No. 52 provide an extensive sampling of documentation of his many activities on the local, national and international levels. Used in conjunction with his autobiographical writings, these papers would lend themselves to a detailed biographical study of Gray. In addition, these papers provide unique and valuable documentation of the merger between Congregational Christian Churches and the Evangelical and Reformed Church to form the United Church of Christ in 1957. Gray was the only former national executive of the Congregational Churches who chose to continue as a Congregationalist rather than join the new denomination. He wrote concerning the merger-related files in this manuscript group:"My "merger" files are the sole complete repository of the "Polity and Unity Committee" (1950-1954) and the "Constitutional Commission" (1954-1956) of the General Council of the Congregational Christian Churches. The "official" records are in The Congregational Library archives. My personal files... included the most extensive survey ever made of Congregational Polity (1954 A.D.) in the basic Documents, and in Practice... Additionally I have complete files on the efforts of the "Mediators" --the 'middle group' in the CC/ER controversy-- of which I was possibly the chief leader. My book The Mediators is the only account of those who tried to reconcile the proponents and opponents of the CC/ER merger.(Letter to Martha Lund Smalley, September 13, 1985, in Special Collections donor file.)
Series I, Personal Files/Correspondence, provides an overview of Henry David Gray's life and work. Mirroring Gray's personal system of filing, the series includes both subject files and letters to or from various individuals. Extensive correspondence with young people and church members with whom Gray worked over the years document the close and warm relationships he formed and the regard in which he was held. A series of bound volumes of letters and other documents in chronological sequence supplement and overlap with the alphabetical sequence of files. Letters from individuals listed in the alphabetical sequence may also appear in the bound volumes. The files of Series I are in many cases complemented by files in other series. The file for Jordan Wen, for example, is related to material available in Series VII under the National Association of Congregational Christian Churches, Commission on Missions.
Series II, Churches Served, provides extensive documentation of the activities of the various congregations that Gray served. These files could be used as case studies of the operation of active Congregational churches in the middle years of this century.
Series III, The Christian Year, documents the method by which Gray organized his ministry in the churches he served. A summary of this method is available in Gray's Congregational Worshipbook, revised edition, 1990, p. 145 ff.
Series IV, Youth Files, documents Gray's long term and intensive involvement with Congregational youth on a local and national level. During the period when Gray served as National Secretary for youth in the Congregational fellowship, he traveled widely throughout the United States, conducting youth rallies, speaking at colleges and contributing to The Pilgrim Highroad, a monthly publication for Congregational youth. The files in Series IV are supplemented by Series V, Odyssey Files, and by Gray's writings for and about youth which are included in Series VI, Writings, Addresses, Sermons.
Series V, Odyssey Files, documents a particular facet of Gray's involvement with youth. Initiating a new form of youth work, Gray began a series of "youth odysseys" abroad in 1948. He wrote regarding the "odysseys": "The basic idea of these journeys is "personalized internationalism." Young people from a local community and local Church in the United States visit in the homes and institutions of young people like themselves in other lands. By personal contact with leaders, and by personal survey of economic, social, political, cultural and religious situations, the young folk come close to their numbers abroad. These Odysseys have taken youth groups to 37 different lands." This series also contains documentation relating to other church youth trips abroad that were offshoots of Gray's odyssey concept.
Series VI, Writings, Addresses, Sermons, documents in a thorough way Gray's many writings and sermons on a variety of subjects. The hundreds of sermons available in this series provide a significant sampling of the work of a Congregational minister over many years. Gray's writings related to the merger controversy in the Congregational churches were widely deseminated and very influential. Gray's writings on historical subjects, such as the Mayflower Pilgrims, are also significant.
Series VII, Congregational Records, contains some of the most interesting material in the collection. A chronological sequence of files related to Congregational polity and the merger that resulted in the formation of the United Church of Christ contains extensive and in some cases unique documentation of a turbulent period in Congregational history. These files are best used in conjunction with Gray's book The Mediators, which provides his commentary on the issues and events involved. The second section of Series VII includes documentation of a wide variety of Congregational organizations with which Gray was involved.
A significant number of pamphlets, books and reports related to Congregationalism that Gray had collected over the years have been added to the Library's Record Group No. 56, Congregational Church Records, or to the Library's general collection in order to insure the greatest possible access to these material by the public. The printed materials retained in Series VII of the Henry David Gray Papers are those which have biographical interest.
Arrangement
I. Personal files/ correspondence
II. Churches served
III. The Christian year
IV. Youth files
V. Odyssey files
VI. Writings, addresses, sermons
VII. Congregational records
Church work with youth; Church year; Congregational churches -- United States; Congregationalism; Sermons, American; Clergy; Conn, Howard (Howard James), 1911-2000; Fifield, James W., 1899-1977; Gray, Henry David, 1908-; Horton, Douglas, 1891-1968; Palmer, Albert W. (Albert Wentworth), 1879-1954; National Association of Congregational Christian Churches (U.S.); Oneonta Congregational Church (South Pasadena, Cal.); South Congregational Church (Hartford, Conn.); United Church of Christ
- Personal Files/Correspondence, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series is divided into two sections:
  Alphabetical Sequence
  Bound Volumes of correspondence, etc.
  - Alphabetical Sequence
    - "A" (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - American Congregational Center (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Anniversary letters (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Arab-Jewish relations (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Arnold, Daniel D. (ordination) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Asfour, Hala (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "B" (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Butrous, Noshi (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Britain - 1945 delegation of Congregationalists to survey war damage (Box 1, Folder 9,10)
    - Britain - 1945 survey follow-up (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Britain - misc., church-related, 2 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Britain - misc., youth-related (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Bryant, Florence (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Burnap, Art (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Butman, Harry (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - "C" (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Church covenants (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Church Homes, Inc. (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Church services - baptism, confirmation (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Church services - dedications, recognition (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Church services - funerals (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Church services - marriage (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Church services - order of worship (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Church services - ordination, installation (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Congregational Journal (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - The Congregationalist (Box 2, Folder 26-28)
    - Connecticut River Valley Theological Club (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Crosby, Ernest and Frances (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - "D" (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Devotional works (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Dole, Fred M. (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Douglas, Isa (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - "E" (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Edinburgh period (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Elmore John (Box 3, Folder 37,38)
    - Evangelism (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - "F" (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Fifield, James W.,Jr / First Congregational Church of Los Angeles (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Film projects (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - "G" (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Gray, Betsey (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Gray David L. (Box 3, Folder 45-47)
    - Gray, Ellen (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - Gray, Helen Lorbeer - correspondence (Box 4, Folder 49-63)
    - Gray, Helen Lorbeer - writings, memorabilia (Box 4, Folder 64)
    - Gray, Henry David - account books (Box 5, Folder 65,66)
    - Gray, Henry David - biographical documentation (Box 5, Folder 67-70)
    - Gray, Henry and Helen - circular letters to friends (Box 5, Folder 71-73)
    - Gray, Henry and Helen - fiftieth wedding anniversary (Box 5, Folder 74)
    - "H" (Box 5, Folder 75)
    - Hartford, CT - Commission on the City Plan (Box 5, Folder 76)
    - Hartford, CT - South Village, Inc. (Box 6, Folder 77-79)
    - Herrick, Mrs. F.E. (mother of Helen) (Box 6, Folder 80)
    - Hissen, Fouad (Box 6, Folder 81)
    - Hollywood Congregational Center for Study and Service (Box 98, Folder 701)
    - "I" (Box 6, Folder 82)
    - "J" (Box 6, Folder 83)
    - "K" (Box 6, Folder 84)
    - "L" (Box 6, Folder 85)
    - "M" (Box 6, Folder 86)
    - MacLeod, Margaret (Box 6, Folder 87)
    - Marriage counseling (Box 6, Folder 88)
    - Mayflower Congregational Church (Box 6, Folder 89)
    - Mead, Cary H. (Box 6, Folder 90)
    - Ministers-in-the-making (Box 7, Folder 91-95)
    - Mt. Holyoke College (Box 7, Folder 96)
    - Murch, James D. (Box 7, Folder 97)
    - "N" (Box 7, Folder 98)
    - Nasir, Kameel and Labib (Box 7, Folder 99)
    - National Council of Churches of Christ in the USA (Box 99, Folder 722)
    - National Council on Religion in Higher Education (Box 7, Folder 100)
    - Near East Foundation (Box 7, Folder 101)
    - "O" (Box 7, Folder 102)
    - Occidental College (Box 7, Folder 103)
    - Olin, Karin (Box 7, Folder 104)
    - Oneonta Club (Box 7, Folder 105)
    - Oneonta Congregational Church (see also SERIES II) - call and arrival (Box 7, Folder 106)
    - Oneonta Congregational Church - post 1955 (Box 7, Folder 107)
    - "P" (Box 7, Folder 108)
    - Papatheodorus, Alexander (Box 8, Folder 109)
    - Pendleton, Morris (Box 8, Folder 110)
    - Photographs - HDG and family (Box 8, Folder 111)
    - Photographs - misc. (Box 8, Folder 112)
    - Photographs - misc. (Box 104, Folder 766)
    - Piedmont College (Box 8, Folder 113)
    - Pilgrim Fellowship (Box 8, Folder 114)
    - Plays and pageants (Box 8, Folder 115)
    - Pomona College, class of 1930 (Box 8, Folder 116)
    - Popular culture (Box 8, Folder 117)
    - Positions offered to HDG (Box 8, Folder 118-120)
    - Potter, Hope (Box 8, Folder 121)
    - Prayers and poems (Box 8, Folder 122)
    - Prentice, Fred (Box 8, Folder 123)
    - Presbyterian Church in the USA, scholarship aid (Box 8, Folder 124)
    - Publishers (Box 8, Folder 125)
    - "R" (Box 9, Folder 126)
    - Roberts, Edwin (Box 9, Folder 127)
    - "S" (Box 9, Folder 128)
    - Samuelson, Robert (Box 9, Folder 129)
    - Smith, Edward H. (Box 9, Folder 129)
    - Society and association memberships of HDG (Box 9, Folder 130)
    - Song sheets (Box 9, Folder 131)
    - South Congregational Church, Hartford (see also SERIES II) - call and arrival (Box 9, Folder 132, 133)
    - Stokes, Kenneth (Box 9, Folder 134)
    - Stowe, David and Virginia (Box 9, Folder 135)
    - Swanson, Neil (Box 9, Folder 136)
    - "T" (Box 9, Folder 137)
    - Travel souvenirs (Box 9, Folder 138)
    - "U" (Box 9, Folder 139)
    - "V" (Box 9, Folder 140)
    - Ventura, California - bicentennial (Box 9, Folder 141)
    - Ventura - city planning (Box 10, Folder 142)
    - Ventura - Community Improvement Committee (Box 10, Folder 143)
    - Ventura - Dudley House (Box 10, Folder 144)
    - Ventura - Historic Preservation Commission (Box 10, Folder 145)
    - Ventura - "An Overview of Heritage - San Buenaventura" (Box 10, Folder 146)
    - Ventura - "A Panorama of Man" (Box 10, Folder 147)
    - Ventura County Environmental Coalition (Box 10, Folder 148)
    - Ventura County Planning Commission (Box 10, Folder 149)
    - "W" (Box 10, Folder 150)
    - Waldensians (Box 10, Folder 151)
    - Welles, Raymond L., Jr. (ordination) (Box 10, Folder 152)
    - Wen, Jordan (Box 10, Folder 153)
    - "Y" (Box 10, Folder 154)
    - Zikas, Phil (Box 10, Folder 155)
  - Bound volumes of correspondence, etc.
    - Pilgrim Fellowship Years, 1939-1942 (Box 11)
    - "Pay Better than Gold", 1948-1954 (Box 11)
    - "Pay Better than Gold", 1949 Nov-1951 Dec (Box 11)
    - "Pay Better than Gold", 1952 (Box 11)
    - "Pay Better than Gold", 1953 (Box 12)
    - "Pay Better than Gold", 1954 (Box 12)
    - "Pay Better than Gold", 1955-1956 (Box 13)
    - "Pay Better than Gold", 1955-1956 (Box 13)
    - "Pay Better than Gold", 1956 (Box 14)
    - "Pay Better than Gold", 1957-1 (Box 14)
    - "Pay Better than Gold", 1957-2 (Box 15)
    - "Pay Better than Gold", 1958 (Box 15)
    - "Pay Better than Gold", 1958 (Box 15)
    - "Pay Better than Gold", 1960 (Box 16)
    - "Pay Better than Gold", 1961 (Box 16)
    - "Pay Better than Gold", 1962 (Box 17)
    - "Pay Better than Gold", 1963 (Box 17)
    - "Pay Better than Gold", 1964-1 (Box 18)
    - "Pay Better than Gold", 1964-2 (Box 18)
    - "Pay Better than Gold", 1965 (Box 19)
    - "Pay Better than Gold", 1966 (Box 19)
    - "Pay Better than Gold", 1967 (Box 20)
    - "Pay Better than Gold", 1968 (Box 21)
- Churches Served, Series II
  Material is included in this series for the following churches:
  First Methodist Episcopal Church, Pomona (1929-1930)
  Asylum Hill Congregational Church, Hartford (1931-1933)
  Hope Park and Buccleuch Congregational Church, Edinburgh (1933-1935)
  First Congregational Church, South Hadley (1935-1939)
  Oneonta Congregational Church, South Pasadena (1942-1955)
  South Congregational Church, Hartford (1955-1971)
  Hollywood Congregational Church (1971)
  Congregational Church of the Valley (1971-1972)
  The extensive files for the Oneonta and South Churches are each divided into two sections:
  A. Alphabetical sequence
  B. Bound volumes
  - Early churches
    - First Methodist Episcopal Church, Pomona, 1929-1930 (Box 22, Folder 156)
    - Asylum Hill Congregational Church, Hartford, 1931-1933 (Box 22, Folder 157)
    - Hope Park and Buccleuch Congregational Church, Edinburgh, 1933-1935 (Box 22, Folder 158)
  - First Congregational Church, South Hadley (1935-1939)
    - Christian education (Box 22, Folder 159)
    - Church bulletins (Box 22, Folder 160, 161)
    - Committees (Box 22, Folder 162)
    - Community activities (Box 22, Folder 163)
    - Correspondence (Box 22, Folder 164)
    - Ordination and installation of HDG (Box 22, Folder 165)
    - Program material (Box 22, Folder 166)
    - Records (Box 23, Folder 167)
    - Youth work (Box 23, Folder 168)
  - Oneonta Congregational Church, South Pasadena (1942-1955)
    - Alphabetical sequence
      - Annual reports (Box 23, Folder 169)
      - Building program
      - Church building (Box 23, Folder 170-172)
      - Church building - Dedication services (Box 23, Folder 173)
      - Church building - Fellowship hall (Box 23, Folder 174-176)
      - Church building - Financing (Box 23, Folder 177-178)
      - Church building - Photographs (Box 23, Folder 179)
      - Church building - Redwood Chapel (Box 23, Folder 180)
      - Christian education (Box 23, Folder 181)
      - Church year program (Box 24, Folder 182, 183)
      - Committees/officers (Box 24, Folder 184)
      - Correspondence (Box 24, Folder 185-189)
      - History and description - Guidebooks (Box 24, Folder 190)
      - History and description - Iconography (Box 24, Folder 191)
      - History and description - Memorial windows (Box 24, Folder 192)
      - History and description - Miscellaneous (Box 24, Folder 193)
      - History and description - Photographs (Box 25, Folder 194, 195)
      - History and description - 75th and other anniversaries (Box 25, Folder 196)
      - Installation of HDG (Box 25, Folder 197)
      - Meeting records (Box 25, Folder 198)
      - Organizational charts (Box 25, Folder 199)
      - Planning/evaluation (Box 25, Folder 200)
      - Post World War II relief contributions (Box 25, Folder 201, 202)
      - Post World War II sponsoring of service worker in Britain (Box 25, Folder 203)
      - Procedure manuals/sheets (Box 25, Folder 204)
      - Program leaflets (Box 25, Folder 205)
      - War Service Committee (Box 25, Folder 206)
      - Worship and service bulletins (Box 25, Folder 207)
      - Youth work (see Series IV)
    - Bound volumes of church records
      - Annual reports, 1943-1953 (Box 26, Folder vol. 1)
      - Board minutes, 1944-1951 (Box 26, Folder vol. 2)
      - Board minutes, 1952-1955 (Box 26, Folder vol. 3)
      - Church year, 1943-1956 (Box 27, Folder vol. 4)
      - Committee reports, 1949-1951 (Box 27, Folder vol. 5)
      - Records, 1950-1952 (Box 27, Folder vol. 6)
      - Records, 1954-1955 (Box 28, Folder vol. 7)
      - finance, 1954-1955 (Box 28, Folder vol. 8)
      - "Oneonta Messenger", 1949 (Box 28, Folder vol. 9)
      - "Oneonta Messenger", 1951 (Box 28, Folder vol. 10)
      - "Oneonta Messenger", 1952 (Box 28, Folder vol. 11)
      - "Oneonta Messenger", 1953 (Box 28, Folder vol. 12)
      - "Oneonta Messenger", 1953-1954 (Box 28, Folder vol. 13)
      - "Oneonta Messenger", 1954-1955 (Box 28, Folder vol. 14)
      - Pilgrim Fellowship Year, 1944-1952 (Box 28, Folder vol. 15)
      - Staff Highlights, 1945-1951 (Box 28, Folder vol. 16)
      - Staff Highlights, 1951-1954 (Box 28, Folder vol. 17)
      - Staff Highlights, 1954-1955 (Box 28, Folder vol. 18)